We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we begin a two-part series
on the effects of fasting on cancer.
Do we feed cancer?
Do we starve it?
What do randomized trials tell us?
Here’s our first story.
In 1974, an influential paper
was published decrying
physician-induced malnutrition as
the skeleton in the hospital closet ---
the fact that many patients in
hospitals were malnourished,
which the editorial board
of the journal of the AMA
described as shocking.
"Even a single case
is one too many,"
yet still to this day
the issue persists.
If anything, people with serious
illness would seem to need
even more nutrition,
not less, yet underfeeding
persists, involving as many as
50% of hospitalized patients.
The ethical principle of justice
requires that every patient
be fed enough, given
that hospital malnutrition
has been associated
with increased
risk of disease and death,
but is it cause and effect?
Does eating less
make you sicker,
or does being sicker
just make you eat less?
You don't know until
you put it to the test.
But would it be ethical to randomize
patients to remain starved?
I mean wouldn't nutritional
support obviously help?
It turns out, no.
Not one,
but 22 randomized controlled
trials involving thousands
of malnourished patients
found that, sure,
you can plump them up;
however, there seemed to be
little effect on clinical outcomes.
In fact, sometimes it can
actually make things worse.
Maybe your body is losing
your appetite on purpose.
Ever since Hippocrates, fasting
has been offered as a treatment
for acute and chronic diseases,
based on the observation
that when people get sick, they
frequently lose their appetite,
so maybe that's part of our body's
wisdom and we shouldn't force it?
OK, but that was 2400 years ago.
What have we learned since?
Along with fever, decreased
food consumption is indeed
one of the most common signs
of infection, often regarded
as an undesirable
manifestation of sickness,
but it's actually an active,
beneficial defense mechanism.
Now obviously, chronic
under-nutrition can impair
our defenses, but data
suggest that in the short-term,
immune function can be enhanced
by lowering food intake.
Some of the data are crazy,
like 95% alive versus 95% dead
after the same infection,
but that was in mice
starved for 48 hours.
Obviously, you can't randomize
people to a fatal infection,
but what they showed is that
the blood from starved mice was
nearly 8 times better at
killing off the invading bacteria
in a petri dish.
It dramatically boosted
the capacity of their white blood
cells to kill off the pathogens.
Why can't we just test people
like that?
Indeed, we can.
Researchers fasted
people for two weeks
on an 80 calorie a day diet,
and their white blood cells
showed the same kind of boost
in bacteria-killing activity,
a boost in antibody production,
and natural killer cell activity
increased by an average of 24%.
Now that's especially interesting
because our natural killer cells
don't just help clear infections,
but also kill cancer cells.
In fact, that's how they measured
natural killer cell activity by pitting
them against K562 cells --- those are
tumor cells, human leukemia cells.
So two weeks of fasting boosted
their bloodstream's ability
to kill off cancer cells by 24%.
So fasting is said to improve
anticancer immunosurveillance,
or more poetically
"stimulate the appetite of
the immune system for cancer.
"
So why isn't fasting used more
to treat cancer?
Until recently,
fasting therapy was not considered
to be a treatment option
in cancer, related to the fact that
a common therapeutic goal
in palliative cancer treatment
is to avoid weight loss
and to counteract the wasting
syndrome known as cachexia,
which is the ultimate cause
of death in many cancer cases.
Tumors are voracious,
rapidly expanding,
and needing lots of
energy and protein,
and so metabolically
reprograms our body
to start breaking down to feed it.
It does this by triggering
inflammation throughout the body.
It's not just that people
lose their appetite.
The fundamental difference
between weight loss
observed in cancer cachexia
and that seen in simple starvation
is the lack of reversibility
with feeding alone.
For example, here's the weight of
a cancer patient that started to drop.
No wonder: they were only taking
in a few hundred calories a day.
So in addition to giving them
about 100 grams of protein a day,
they stuck a tube into a vein and
infused up to 4,000 calories a day.
But it didn't matter.
They continued to lose weight.
Therapeutic nutritional
interventions to correct or reverse
cachexia have met
with little success.
The best treatment for
cancer cachexia therefore
is to treat the cause
and cure the cancer.
In fact, maybe forcing extra
nutrition on cancer patients
could be playing right
into the tumor's hands.
Like in pregnancy when the
fetus gets first dibs on nutrients
even at the mother's expense,
the tumor may be first
in the feeding line.
Maybe our loss of appetite
when we get cancer
is even a protective response.
But in the 1960s, TPN was born ---
total parenteral nutrition ---
where people no
longer had to eat;
and you could infuse all the
nutrition people needed straight
into their veins, and the modern
era of nutrition support was born.
It became widely accepted
and implemented,
growing into a
multibillion-dollar industry.
So should it be routinely given to
malnourished cancer patients?
The answer is not as
obvious as one might think.
When it was put to the test
in dozens of randomized trials,
the results were both
disappointing and surprising.
Parenteral nutrition didn't just
fail to provide any benefit
to these patients;
it caused harm.
Not only did it appear to
provide zero survival benefit,
there was an increase in
complications and infections,
and a decrease in tumor
response to chemotherapy,
presumed to be due to all
those extra nutrients
stimulating tumor growth.
Similarly, oral nutritional
interventions in malnourished
patients with cancer,
like giving them bottles of Ensure,
found no survival advantage.
Despite the lack of demonstrated
benefit, the knee jerk reaction
of many oncologists to the idea
of cancer patients fasting
is the concern they're not
eating enough already.
But you don't know until you
until you put it to the test,
which we'll explore next.
For the past 50 years, chemotherapy
has been a major medical treatment
for a wide range of cancers.
Its main strategy has been largely
based on targeting cancer cells,
by means of DNA damage
caused in part by the
production of free radicals.
Although these drugs
were first believed to be
quite selective for tumor cells,
we now know that normal cells
also experience severe
chemotherapy-dependent damage,
leading to dose-limiting side effects
including bone marrow and
immune system suppression,
fatigue, vomiting, diarrhea,
and in some cases even death.
And if you do survive, the DNA
damage to normal cells
can even lead to new
cancers down the road.
There are cell-protecting
drugs that have been tried
to reduce the side effects,
so you can pump in
higher chemo doses,
but these drugs have not been
shown to increase survival,
in part because they may also
be protecting the cancer cells.
What about instead using fasting
for cellular protection
during cancer treatment?
Fasting may have
an unrecognized role
in cancer prevention and treatment.
Short-term fasting before and
immediately after chemotherapy
may minimize side effects,
while at the same time
may actually make cancer cells
more sensitive to treatment.
That's exciting.
During nutrient deprivation,
healthy cells switch from growth
to maintenance and repair,
but tumor cells are unable
to slow down their unbridled growth
due to growth-promoting mutations
that led them to become
cancer cells in the first place.
This inability to adapt to starvation
may represent an important
Achilles' heel for many
types of cancer cells.
As a consequence of these
differential responses
of healthy versus cancer
cells to short-term fasting,
chemotherapy causes more
DNA damage and cell suicide
in tumor cells, while potentially
leaving healthy cells unharmed.
Thus, short-term fasting
may protect healthy cells
against the toxic properties
of chemotherapy
and render tumor cells
more sensitive,
or at least that's the theory.
Let's test it out.
Tyrosine kinase inhibitors
are a group of chemo drugs
that are now the mainstay of
treatment in many types of cancer.
Let's see them in action.
These are petri dishes
filled with cancer cells that
have been dyed pink.
Two types of lung cancer cells
and one type of colorectal cancer.
This is the before, and this the
after, exposed to the chemo drugs
erlotinib, gefitinib, crizotinib,
and regorafenib.
See how there's less pink?
That shows how many cancer
cells the chemo killed off.
Starve the cells for
24 hours first, though,
and the drugs work even better.
Even the starvation alone without
the drugs killed off a bunch of them.
The researchers conclude
that these TKI drugs that are
commonly administrated for
treating solid tumors become
potentiated in their activity
by 24 hours of starvation,
but that's in a petri dish.
Similar results were found
for breast cancer and
a chemo drug called doxorubicin.
Here's five days of unhindered growth
of breast cancer in a petri dish,
from 150,000 cancer cells
to 800,000 in under a week.
Dripping on a little chemo can
knock it down to around 600,000,
but starve those cells
for 48 hours first,
and the chemo can completely
keep them in check.
Even the short-term starvation
alone can restrain growth.
Short-term fasting raises the
possibility that you could get
twice the effect for half the dose,
which may be particularly important
for a drug as toxic as doxorubicin,
which causes heart failure
in as many as 1 in 3 at higher doses.
Again, though, these are just
in vitro studies in a petri dish
Then researchers moved to mice
and found the same dual benefit:
less toxic chemo,
yet at the same time
more effective,
and not just by a little.
A high enough chemo dose
to kill 100% in less than a week.
But after being starved for 60 hours,
after the same dose, 100% survived.
Ok, that's the toxicity.
What about efficacy?
Here's tumor growth without
chemo, growth with chemo,
and with chemo after
short-term fasting,
and this translated
into improved survival.
Interestingly, fasting alone
appeared to work
as well as the chemo,
and the same with radiation.
Unbridled tumor growth knocked
down by radiation therapy,
and even more so after
the combination of radiation
and alternate-day fasting,
but alternate-day fasting alone
seemed to do as well as the radiation.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.